<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The last speeches of the five notorious traitors and Jesuits viz. Thomas White ... William Harcourt ... John Gavan ... Anthony Turner and John Fenwick ... who were justly executed at Tyburn, June 20, 1679, for conspiring the death of His Sacred Majesty, and the subversion of the government and Protestant religion.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1697</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 33 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A49654</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L506</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R32875</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12775409</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12775409</idno>
            <idno type="VID">93758</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A49654)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 93758)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1036:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The last speeches of the five notorious traitors and Jesuits viz. Thomas White ... William Harcourt ... John Gavan ... Anthony Turner and John Fenwick ... who were justly executed at Tyburn, June 20, 1679, for conspiring the death of His Sacred Majesty, and the subversion of the government and Protestant religion.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p.,   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1697]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint suggested by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Charles II, 1660-1685.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:93758:1"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:93758:1"/>
            <head>THE LAST SPEECHES OF THE FIVE NOTORIOUS <hi>Traitors and Jeſuits:</hi> VIZ.
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Thomas White</hi> aliàs <hi>Whitebread,</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincial of the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> in <hi>England.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>William Harcourt</hi> aliàs <hi>Harriſon,</hi> pretended Rector of <hi>London.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>John Gavan</hi> aliàs <hi>Gawen.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Anthony Turner.</hi> And</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>John Fenwick,</hi> Procurator for the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> in <hi>England.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </head>
            <argument>
               <p>Who were juſtly Executed at <hi>Tyburn, June 20. 1679.</hi> for Conſpiring the Death of His Sacred Majeſty, and the Subverſion of the Government and Proteſtant Religion.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>IF the moſt ignorant of Criminals, when Condemned to dye, and juſt ready to undergo the deſerved puniſhment of their Offences, are always ambitious to extenuate the Enormitie of their Crimes, wonder not then, that they who have aſſum'd to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves the dignify'd Orders of Religion and Sanctitie, together with the perfections of noble Learning; and under that Notion and Coverture, to eſtabliſh themſelves in the abſolute Dominion of the Souls, and conſequently the Bodies of Men; break all the Fences and impalements of Divinity and Morality, and being brought to ſuffer for their ſo doing, make it their buſineſs to impoſe upon the Spectators of their laſt Behaviour. Thoſe people know that the laſt words of dying Men bear a great ſway amongſt the Living, and that the ſwanlike ſentences of thoſe that ſing at their departure, being cunningly inſinuated and politickly made uſe of, penetrate more deeply than can be imagin'd into the hearts of the credulous and unſtable. Upon theſe grounds, and with theſe aims, thoſe Perſons ſo lately condemn'd by National Juſtice, and warranted to execution, like Men infected with the Peſtilence, who through the particular malice of that diſtemper labour to infect all Perſons that they come near, thought to have impos'd their deluſions upon the people, and by their ultimate Farwels to the World, to have diffus'd the venom of their Hereſie through the Veins of the whole Nation. For could they but have purg'd away their Crimes with the ſweet Hyſop of a fine ſpeech, or blotted out the ſtains of their Offences with an inveagling Metaphor, then they thought they had done a great work: well knowing, that an Opinion of Martyrdom begets Belief, and that Belief is the Mother of Converſion. Thereby they had improv'd their Happineſs in conceit, and had ſhort'ned their journey to Heaven by leaving Purgatory on the left hand, as being ſuch who had given a more deadly ſtroke, like <hi>Sampſon,</hi> to their Enemies, at their fall, than all the years of their former lives e're gave them opportunity to do. But to prevent their intended miſchief, and to advance an Antidote againſt the ſpreading venom of clandeſtine Tranſcripts conveyed from Perſon to Perſon, and conſequently ſubject to thoſe alterations, additions, and diminutions, as may be moſt advantageous to the interpreter, it may be preſum'd an Act of prudence to divulge in ſeaſon the moſt exact Copies of theſe ſpeeches which were intended for no good. An act the rather to be juſtified, in regard the beſt Phyſicians always firſt deſcribe the diſtemper at large, and then ſet down the preſcription of the Cure. Nor can it be unacceptable to good Government, by lawful means to prevent the people from being deceiv'd, where their deception may entice them to Change and Diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience.</p>
            <div type="speech">
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:93758:2"/>
               <head>The laſt Speech of <hi>Thomas White,</hi> aliàs <hi>Whitebread.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>I Suppoſe it is expected I ſhould ſpeak ſomething to the matter I am condemned for, and brought hither to ſuffer, it is no leſs than the contriving and plotting His Majeſty's Death, and the alteration of the Government of the Church and State; you all either know, or ought to know, I am to make my appearance before the Face of Almighty God, and with all imaginable certainty and evidence to receive a final Judgment, for all the thoughts, words, and actions of my whole life: So that I am not now upon terms to ſpeak other than truth, and therefore in his moſt Holy Preſence, and as I hope for Mercy from his Divine Majeſty, I do declare to you here preſent, and to the whole World, that I go out of the World as inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, and as free from any guilt of theſe things laid to my charge in this matter, as I came into the World from my Mother's Womb; and that I do renounce from my heart all manner of Pardons, Abſolutions, Diſpenſations for Swearing, as occaſions or Intereſt may ſeem to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire, which ſome have been pleaſed to lay to our charge as matter of our Practice and Doctrine, but is a thing ſo unjuſtifiable and unlawful, that I believe, and ever did, that no power on Earth can authorize me, or any body ſo to do; and for thoſe who have ſo falſly accuſed me (as time, either in this World, or in the next, will make appear) I do heartily forgive them, and beg of God to grant them his holy Grace, that they may repent their unjuſt proceedings againſt me, otherwiſe they will in concluſion find they have done themſelves more wrong than I have ſuffered from them, though that has been a great deal. I pray God bleſs His Majeſty both Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral and Eternal, which has been my daily Prayers for him, and is all the harm that I ever intended or imagined againſt him. And I do with this my laſt breath in the ſight of God de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare, that I never did learn, teach, or believe, that it is lawful upon any occaſion or pretence whatſoever, to deſign or contrive the Death of His Majeſty, or any hurt to his Perſon; but on the contrary, all are bound to obey, defend, and preſerve his Sacred Perſon, to the utmoſt of their power. And I do moreover declare, that this is the true and plain ſence of my Soul in the ſight of him who knows the Secrets of my Heart, and as I hope to ſee his bleſſed Face without any Equivocation, or mental Reſervation. This is all I have to ſay concerning the matter of my Condemnation, that which remains for me now to do, is to recommend my Soul into the hands of my bleſſed Redeemer, by whoſe only Merits and Paſſion I hope for Salvation.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="speech">
               <head>The laſt Speech of <hi>William Harcourt,</hi> aliàs <hi>Harriſon.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THE words of dying perſons have been always eſteem'd as of greateſt Authority, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe uttered then, when ſhortly after they were to be cited before the high Tribunal of Almighty God, this gives me hopes that mine may be look'd upon as ſuch, therefore I do here declare in the preſence of Almighty God, and the whole Court of Heaven, and this numerous Aſſembly, that as I ever hope (by the Merits and Paſſion of my ſweet Saviour Jeſus Chriſt) for Eternal Bliſs, I am as innocent as the Child unborn of any thing laid to my charge, and for which I am here to dye, and I do utterly abhor and deteſt that abominable falſe Doctrine laid to our charge, that we can have Licenſes to commit perjury, or any Sin to advantage our cauſe, being expreſly againſt the Doctrine of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> ſaying, <hi>Non ſunt faci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enda mala, ut eveniant bona;</hi> Evil is not to be done that good may come thereof. And therefore we hold it in all caſes unlawful to kill or murder any perſon whatſoever, much more our law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful King now Reigning, whoſe perſonal and temporal Dominions we are ready to defend againſt any Opponent whatſoever, none excepted. I forgive all that have contriv'd my Death, and humbly beg pardon of Almighty God. I alſo pardon all the World. I pray God bleſs His Majeſty, and grant him a proſperous Reign. The like I wiſh to his Royal Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſort the beſt of Queens. I humbly beg the Prayers of all thoſe of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, if any ſuch be preſent.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="speech">
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:93758:2"/>
               <head>The laſt Speech of <hi>John Gavan,</hi> aliàs <hi>Gawen.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>DEarly beloved Country-men, I am come now to the laſt Scene of Mortality, to the hour of my Death, an hour which is the Horizon between Time and Eternity, an hour which muſt either make me a Star to ſhine for ever in the Empyreum above, or a Firebrand to burn ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſtingly amongſt the damned Souls in Hell below; an hour in which if I deal ſincerely, and with a hearty ſorrow acknowledge my crimes, I may hope for mercy; but if I falſly deny them, I muſt expect nothing but Eternal Damnation; and therefore what I ſhall ſay in this great hour, I hope you will believe. And now in this hour I do ſolemnly ſwear, proteſt, and vow, by all that is Sacred in Heaven and on Earth, and as I hope to ſee the Face of God in Glory, that I am as innocent as the Child unborn of thoſe treaſonable Crimes, which Mr. <hi>Oates</hi> and Mr. <hi>Dugdale</hi> have Sworn againſt me in my Tryal, and for which, ſentence of Death was pronounced againſt me the day after my Tryal; and that you may be aſſured that what I ſay is true, I do in the like manner proteſt, vow, and ſwear, as I hope to ſee the Face of God in Glory, that I do not in what I ſay unto you, make uſe of any Equivocation, mental Reſervation, and material Prolocution, or any ſuch ways to palliate Truth. Neither do I make uſe of any diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions from the Pope, or any body elſe; or of any Oath of ſecreſie, or any abſolution in Confeſſion or out of Confeſſion to deny the truth, but I ſpeak in the plain ſence which the words bear; and if I do not ſpeak in the plain ſence which the words bear, or if I do ſpeak in any other terms to palliate, hide, or deny the truth, I wiſh with all my Soul that God may exclude me from his Heavenly Glory, and condemn me to the loweſt place of Hell Fire: and ſo much to that point.</p>
               <p>And now, dear Country-men, in the ſecond place, I do confeſs and own to the whole World that I am a Roman Catholick, and a Prieſt, and one of that ſort of Prieſts which you call <hi>Jeſuits;</hi> and now becauſe they are ſo falſly charged for holding King-killing Doctrine, I think it my duty to proteſt to you with my laſt dying words, that neither I in particular, nor the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> in general, hold any ſuch opinion, but utterly abhor and deteſt it; and I aſſure you, that among the multitude of Authors, which among the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> have printed Philoſophy, Divinity, Caſes or Sermons, there is not one to the beſt of my knowledge that allows of King-killing Doctrine, or holds this poſition, That it is lawful for a private perſon to kill a King, although an Heretick, although a Pagan, although a Tyrant, there is, I ſay, not one <hi>Jeſuit</hi> that holds this, except <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riana,</hi> the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Jeſuit, and he defends it not abſolutely, but only problematically, for which his Book was called in again, and the opinions expugned and ſentenced. And is it not a ſad thing, that for the raſhneſs of one ſingle Man, whilſt the reſt cry out againſt him, and hold the contrary, that a whole Religious Order ſhould be ſentenc'd? But I have not time to diſcuſs this point at large, and therefore I refer you all to a Royal Author, I mean the wife and victorious King <hi>Henry</hi> the Fourth of <hi>France,</hi> the Royal Grandfather of our preſent gracious King, in a publick Oration which he pronounced himſelf in defence of the <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> ſaid, that he was very well ſatisfied with the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> Doctrine concerning Kings, as believing conformable to what the beſt Doctors of the Church have taught. But why do I relate the teſtimony of one particular Prince, when the whole Catholick World is the <hi>Jeſuit</hi>'s Advocate? for to them chiefly <hi>Germany, France, Italy, Spain,</hi> and <hi>Flanders,</hi> truſt the Education of their Youth, and to them in a great proportion, they truſt their own Souls to be governed in the Sacraments. And can you imagin ſo many great Kings and Princes, and ſo many wiſe States ſhould do or permit this to be done in their Kingdoms, if the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> were men of ſuch damnable principles as they are now taken for in <hi>England?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the third place, dear Country-men, I do atteſt, that as I never in my life did machine, or contrive either the depoſition or death of the King, ſo now I do heartily deſire of God to grant him a quiet and happy Reign upon Earth, and an Everlaſting Crown in Heaven. For the Judges alſo, and the Jury, and all thoſe that were any ways concern'd, either in my Tryal, Accuſation, or Condemnation, I do humbly ask of God, both Temporal and Eternal happineſs. And as for Mr. <hi>Oates</hi> and Mr. <hi>Dugdale,</hi> whom I call God to witneſs, by falſe Oaths have brought me to this untimely end, I heartily forgive them, becauſe God commands me ſo to do; and I beg of God for his infinite Mercy to grant them true Sorrow
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:93758:3"/> and Repentance in this World, that they be capable of Eternal happineſs in the next. And ſo having diſcharged my Duty towards my ſelf, and my own Innocence towards my Order, and its Doctrine to my Neighbour and the World, I have nothing elſe to do now, my great God, but to caſt my ſelf into the Arms of your Mercy, as firmly as I judge that I my ſelf am, as certainly as I believe you are One Divine Eſſence and Three Divine Perſons, and in the Second Perſon of your Trinity you became Man to redeem me; I alſo believe you are an Eternal Rewarder of Good, and Chaſtiſer of Bad. In fine, I believe all you have reveal'd for your own infinite Veracity; I hope in you above all things, for your infinite Fidelity; and I love you above all things, for your infinite Beauty and Goodneſs; and I am heartily ſorry that ever I offended ſo great a God with my whole heart: I am contented to undergo an ignominious Death for the love of you, my dear Jeſu, ſeeing you have been pleaſed to undergo an ignominious Death for the love of me.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="speech">
               <head>The laſt Speech of <hi>Anthony Turner.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>BEing now, good People, very near my End, and ſummon'd by a violent Death to appear before God's Tribunal, there to render an account of all my thoughts, words, and actions, before a juſt Judge, I am bound in Conſcience to declare upon Oath my Innocence from the horrid Crime of Treaſon, with which I am falſely accuſed: And I eſteem it a Duty I owe to Chriſtian Charity, to publiſh to the World before my death all that I know in this point, concerning thoſe Catholicks I have converſed with ſince the firſt noiſe of the Plot, deſiring from the very bottom of my heart, that the whole Truth may appear, that Innocence may be clear'd, to the great Glory of God, and the Peace and Welfare of the King and Country. As for my ſelf, I call God to witneſs, that I was never in my whole life at any Conſult or Meeting of the <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> where any Oath of Secrecy was taken, or the Sacrament, as a Bond of Secrecy, either by me or any one of them, to conceal any Plot againſt His Sacred Majeſty; nor was I ever preſent at any Meeting or Conſult of theirs, where any Propoſal was made, or Reſolve taken or ſigned, either by me or any of them, for taking away the Life of our Dread Soveraign; an Impiety of ſuch a nature, that had I been preſent at any ſuch Meeting, I ſhould have been bound by the Laws of God, and by the Principles of my Religion, (and by God's Grace would have acted accordingly) to have diſcovered ſuch a devilliſh Treaſon to the Civil Magiſtrate, to the end they might have been brought to condign puniſhment. I was ſo far, good People, from being in <hi>September</hi> laſt at a Conſult of the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> at <hi>Tixall,</hi> in Mr. <hi>Ewer</hi>'s Chamber, that I vow to God, as I hope for Salvation, I never was ſo much as once that year at <hi>Tixall,</hi> my Lord <hi>Aſton</hi>'s Houſe. 'Tis true, I was at the Congregation of the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> held on the <hi>24th</hi> of <hi>April</hi> was twelve-month, but in that Meeting, as I hope to be ſaved, we meddled not with State-Affairs, but only treated about the Governours of the Province, which is uſually done by us, without offence to temporal Princes, every third Year all the World over. I am, good People, as free from the Treaſon I am accuſed of, as the Child that is unborn, and being innocent I never accuſed my ſelf in Confeſſion of any thing that I am charged with. Which certainly, if I had been conſcious to my ſelf of any Guilt in this kind, I ſhould not ſo frankly and freely, as I did, of my own accord, preſented my ſelf before the King's Moſt Honourable Privy Council. As for thoſe Catholicks, which I have converſed with ſince the noiſe of the Plot, I proteſt before God, in the words of a dying Man, that I never heard any one of them, neither Prieſt nor Layman, expreſs to me the leaſt knowledge of any Plot, that was then on foot amongſt the Catholicks, againſt the King's Moſt Excellent Majeſty, for the advancing the Catholick Religion. I dye a <hi>Roman</hi> Catholick, and humbly beg the Prayers of ſuch for my happy paſſage into a better Life: I have been of that Religion above Thirty Years, and now give God Almighty infinite thanks for calling me by his holy Grace to the knowledge of this Truth, notwithſtanding the prejudice of my former Education. God of his infinite Goodneſs bleſs the King, and all the Royal Family, and grant His Majeſty a proſperous Reign here, and a Crown of Glory hereafter. God in his mercy forgive all thoſe which have falſely accuſed me, or have had any hand in my Death; I forgive them from the bottom of my heart, as I hope my ſelf for forgiveneſs at the Hands of God.</p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:93758:3"/>
               <p> O GOD who haſt created me to a ſupernatural end, to ſerve thee in this life by grace and injoy thee in the next by glory, be pleaſed to grant by the merits of thy bitter death and paſſion, that after this wretched life ſhall be ended, I may not fail of a full injoyment of thee my laſt end and ſoveraign good. I humbly beg pardon for all the ſins which I have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted againſt thy Divine Majeſty, ſince the firſt Inſtance I came to the uſe of reaſon to this very time; I am heartily ſorry from the very bottom of my heart for having offending thee ſo good, ſo powerfull, ſo wiſe, and ſo juſt a God, and purpoſe by the help of thy grace, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver more to offend thee my good God, whom I love above all things.</p>
               <p>O ſweet Jeſus, who hath ſuffer'd a moſt painfull and ignominious Death upon the Croſs for our Salvation, apply, I beſeech thee, unto me the merits of thy ſacred Paſſion, and ſanctifie unto me theſe ſufferings of mine, which I humbly accept of for thy ſake in union of the ſufferings of thy ſacred Majeſty, and in puniſhment and ſatisfaction of my ſins.</p>
               <p>O my dear Saviour and Redeemer, I return thee immortal thanks for all thou haſt pleaſed to do for me in the whole courſe of my life, and now in the hour of my death, with a firm belief of all things thou haſt revealed, and a ſtedfaſt hope of obteining everlaſting bliſs. I chearfully caſt my ſelf into the Arms of thy Mercy, whoſe Arms were ſtretched on the Croſs for my Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption. Sweet Jeſus receive my Spirit.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="speech">
               <head>The laſt Speech of <hi>John Fenwick.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>GOod People, I ſuppoſe you expect I ſhould ſay ſomething as to the Crime I am Condemned for, and either acknowledge my Guilt, or aſſert my Innocency; I do therefore declare before God and the whole World, and call God to wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs that what I ſay is true, that I am innocent of what is laid to my Charge of Plotting the King's Death, and endeavoring to ſubvert the Government, and bring in a fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Power, as the Child unborn; and that I know nothing of it, but what I have learn'd from Mr. <hi>Oates</hi> and his Companions, and what comes originally from them. And to what is ſaid and commonly believed of <hi>Roman</hi> Catholicks, that they are not to be believed or truſted, becauſe they can have Diſpenſations for Lying, Perjury, killing Kings, and other the moſt enormous Crimes; I do utterly renounce all ſuch Pardons, Diſpenſations, and withall declare, That it is a moſt wicked and malicious Calumny caſt on them, who do all with all their hearts and ſouls hate and deteſt all ſuch wicked and damnable Practiſes, and in the words of a dying Man, and as I hope for Mercy at the hands of God, before whom I muſt ſhortly appear and give an account of all my actions, I do again declare, That what I have ſaid is moſt true, and I hope Chriſtian Charity will not let you think, that by the laſt act of my Life, I would caſt away my Soul, by ſealing up my laſt Breath with a damnable Lye.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="discussion">
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:93758:4"/>
               <p>THe main Drift and Scope of theſe ſo notorious Malefactors Speeches, was to wipe away the Contamination of that Guilt, which brought them all to be the publick Spectacles of Condign Puniſhment; wherein they obſerve all the ſame method of Appealing to Heaven, denying the Doctrine and Maxims of their <hi>Order,</hi> and then praying for the King and themſelves. All which Oaths and Proteſtations, had they been true, they might rather have been thought <hi>Apostates</hi> from their <hi>Order,</hi> and deſertors of the Religion they ſo zealouſly profeſſed upon the Ladder, than valiant Champions of the Romiſh Militant Church. Had they been ſuch Weak and Puſillanimous Combatants with Death, as not ſtrenuouſly to deny what they were ſo fairly convicted of; they would have been deprived of thoſe glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Crowns of Martyrdom which were aſſured them by Him, whom they call the only Lord of all the World, the only Vice-God, the only Emperour, the only King, the Moſt Holy Pope. They thought it was much better to make but one Skip from the Cart to <hi>Jacobs</hi> Ladder, and ſo to mount directly up to Heaven, than to be condemned with an ignominious Load of Truth, and Penitent Confeſſions of the Facts they Committed, to the Whips and Scourges of a tedious Purgatory; elſe it would ſeem ſtrange to the World, that in the midd'ſt of thoſe ſolemn Proteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions which they made to that God, to whom their Souls were taking ſuch a ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy flight, as they pretended, ſhould ſo boldly deny what ſo many Grand-Signiours of Jeſuitiſme have ſo ſtifly maintained to all the World. Nor did this <hi>Leaſh</hi> and <hi>Brace</hi> of their Diſciples, ſhew themſelves ſuch mild Receders from their Principles, who durſt ſo confidently adventure to Beard the Laws and Statutes of a Soveraign Prince, within his own Dominions; <hi>ipſo facto,</hi> Malefactors and Rebels to His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty, when they firſt ſet Foot upon His Shore.</p>
               <p>As for their renouncing all Equivocations and Mental Reſervations, which is the Ground upon which they all tread, that will ſignifie nothing, when we conſider the Nature and Quality of a true <hi>Jeſuite,</hi> which is, tenaciouſly to hold and adhere to the Dictates and Poſitions of their Superiours, as believing what they teach to be all Inſpiration. Now their Heavenly Doctrine is no more than this; that it is lawful for them, not only to deny and conceal the truth, but alſo piouſly and reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giouſly to affirm, to ſwear by, and invoke God and their Salvation to atteſt thoſe things which they know to be aſſuredly untrue. Thus <hi>Toletus,</hi> both a Jeſuite and Cardinal, <hi>L.</hi> 4, of his Inſtructions to the Prieſts, <hi>C. 21. If it be a ſecret Crime con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning which, any one is examined, he may make uſe of Equivocation. As for Example, if I be asked whether I did ſuch a thing or No? I may anſwer No: with this reſervation to my ſelf; I did not</hi> now <hi>do it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Gregory de Valentia</hi> aſſerts the ſame: <hi>If the Queſtion,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>be not fit to be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, though you be upon your Oath, yet ſhall no Perjurie be committed, though the party ſwear contrary to the Intent of the Judge; ſuch a one does neither lye, nor take the Name of God in vain, when it is for his own Preſervation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Andreas Eudemon Johannes</hi> is another of the ſame Stamp.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Martin Azpilcueta</hi> of <hi>Navarr,</hi> proves Equivocation to be lawful, from the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of St. <hi>Francis,</hi> who being asked by certain Officers, <hi>whether ſuch a Murderer did not run ſuch away? Put his hands into his Sleeves, and cried, he did not paſs this way: meaning, that he did not flie through his Sleeves.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The fore-mentioned Cardinal <hi>Toletus</hi> alſo affirms, <hi>That if a Prieſt be asked by the Magiſtrate, whether he ſaw ſuch a one at any time? He may anſwer,</hi> No, <hi>For he did not ſee him that he ſhould tell the Magiſtrate; or he did not ſee him in a Beatifical Viſion, or I did not ſee him at Venice,</hi> &amp;c. Many more Examples might be brought out of the ſame, and ſeveral other Printed Authors; neither are the Equivocations of <hi>Treſham, Garnet,</hi> and others unknown to our ſelves, as thoſe of <hi>Richeome</hi> are in
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:93758:4"/> 
                  <hi>France,</hi> who affirmed <hi>That he never heard the last deceaſed</hi> Henry, <hi>called Tyrant by any of his Subjects, though he had heard</hi> Henry Valois, <hi>the laſt Murdered King often ſo reviled.</hi> So that it may be well ſaid to be the Jeſuits Motto,</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>Jura, perjura, ſecretum prodere Noli.</l>
                  <l>Swear and Forſwear—</l>
                  <l>But the main Secret to betray forbear.</l>
               </lg>
               <p>Thus while they pretend to renounce and deteſt Equivocations, Mental Reſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and Diſpenſations; Reaſon it ſelf muſt needs perſwade us, that Men principl'd and educated by ſuch Inſtructors, are guarded with a good <hi>Salvo,</hi> for thoſe very Equivocations which they ſeemed to abjure.</p>
               <p>No leſs, if not more apparent is the fallacy of their diſowning and diſavowing that Diſmal Doctrine, of killing Kings and Princes.</p>
               <p>To which purpoſe <hi>Gawen</hi> fell ſhort in affirming, that only <hi>Mariana</hi> the <hi>Spaniard</hi> was the upholder of that dreadful Opinion; witneſs the Writings and Approbations of <hi>Stapleton</hi> and <hi>Garnet;</hi> and the Apology of <hi>Jacob Clements,</hi> in ſome part recited in the Oration to the King of <hi>France,</hi> againſt the Readmiſſion of the Jeſuits into that Kingdom. <hi>Commolet</hi> and <hi>Guignardus,</hi> by whom that bloody Act of <hi>Jacob Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> who Murdered <hi>Henry</hi> the Third of <hi>France,</hi> was called the <hi>Gift of the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> as is averr'd in the forementioned Oration to <hi>Henry</hi> the Fourth. <hi>And who ſo wicked among us,</hi> ſaith the ſame Oration, <hi>as not to ſee, that if</hi> Jacob Clements <hi>had not deeply drank of the Jeſuits Poyſon, he would ever have thought of killing his Lord and Maſter.</hi> The Warlike Proweſs and renown of <hi>Henry</hi> the Fourth, could not defend him from the Treachery of a Bejeſuited Enthuſiaſt, who confeſs'd that he had ſuckt all his King-killing malice from their Diabolical Oratory. And ſo far was <hi>Mariana</hi> from being the ſole ſupporter of this Doctrine, that <hi>Francis de Verone</hi> wrote in the defence of <hi>Chaſtell,</hi> who had ſtabb'd <hi>Henry</hi> the Fourth, and <hi>John Gueret</hi> and <hi>John Hay</hi> were both baniſh'd out of <hi>France,</hi> for publickly teaching their Diſciples the vicious Precepts of early Treaſon.</p>
               <p>Nor is there any thing more horrid among all the Butcheries of the Heathen Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crificers, than the Ceremony, which the Jeſuits uſe, at the Conſecration of the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and the Dagger, which they deſign for a Royal Maſſacre. For the intended Executioner is brought into a private Room, where the Dagger carefully wrapt up in a fair Linnen Cloth, and ſheath'd in an Ivory ſheath enamel'd with ſeveral ſtrange Characters, with an <hi>Agnus Dei appendant,</hi> is ſet at liberty to dazle the Murderers eyes. Then the Weapon being drawn, is ſprinkl'd with Holy Water, adorn'd with a Roſarie of Coral Beads, and ſo deliver'd with theſe words. <hi>Choſen Son of God, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Sword of</hi> Jeptha, <hi>the Sword of</hi> Sampſon, <hi>the Sword of</hi> David <hi>with which he cut off</hi> Goliah's <hi>Head</hi> &amp;c. <hi>go and be prudently couragious.</hi> Then falling on their knees, they mumble forth this diſmal exorciſm; <hi>Cherubims and Scraphims, ye Thrones and Powers, ye Holy Angels all deſcend, and fill this bleſsed Veſsel with perpetual Glory; dayly offer to him the Crown of the Bleſſed Virgin</hi> Mary, <hi>the Holy Patriarchs and Martyrs; For he is now your own, and no longer belongs to us.</hi> Then they bring him to the Altar, and ſhewing him the Picture of <hi>Jacob Clements. Strengthen, O Lord</hi> they cry, <hi>this thy Arm, the Inſtrument of thy revenge. Let all the Saints ariſe and give place to Him.</hi> An invention of Men worſe than Devils, enough to amaze Heaven it ſelf; which ſhews that the words of dying men are not always Oracles, when they go about to palliate embodyed Villany. Nor was <hi>Mariana</hi>'s Book exploded, as <hi>Gawen</hi> averrs; but it is true that care was taken by the Jeſuits to ſuppreſs both <hi>Mariana</hi> and others, for he was not alone, meerly out of neceſſity, and to divert the ſtorm that threaten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them from the Court of <hi>France.</hi> And thus the world may ſee the folly of that vain Complement; <hi>That a whole Order ſhould ſuffer for the raſhneſs of one man.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:93758:5"/>
               <p>As little cauſe there is for Us to believe, <hi>That the whole Catholick World</hi> ſhould be the <hi>Jeſuits Advocate.</hi> At leaſt the whole <hi>Catholick World</hi> has taken a very ill Cauſe in hand, to defend an <hi>Order</hi> that has ſo ill behav'd it ſelf, as to be expell'd out of <hi>France</hi> for Murther; out of <hi>England</hi> for High-Treaſon; from <hi>Venice,</hi> almoſt in the ſight of <hi>Rome</hi> it ſelf, for their inſufferable Ambition, and deſigns of Bloody revenge; out of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> for being common Diſturbers of the Publick Peace; out of <hi>Moravia</hi> and <hi>Hungaria</hi> for the ſame Cauſe; out of <hi>Tranſilvania,</hi> for being almoſt the ruin of that Country; and out of the <hi>Low Countries,</hi> for their continual Miſdemeanors; and Laſtly, this may be alſo added, That <hi>Ferdinand</hi> King of <hi>Sweden</hi> was expelled his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, for endeavouring to obtain their readmiſſion after they had been ejected by his Subjects.</p>
               <p>As for Father <hi>Harcourt,</hi> let it not ſeem ſtrange, for I find they were all alike in haſt to reach Heaven before Sun-ſet, that he ſhould pretend ſo much ignorance of the Plot. For the reaſon is plain; he was reſolv'd to Viſit S. <hi>Peter</hi> in the Jeſuits Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very, and to let them ſee he was True Blew: while his own Letter under his own Hand, written into the Country to give notice of Sir <hi>Edmund bury Godfrey</hi>'s Death, three Hours after his Murther; and publickly to be ſeen, puts a moſt cruel Slur upon his late proteſted Hatred of Mental Reſervation and Equivocation.</p>
               <p>Now as for their Prayers for their Judges, and the Diſcoverers of their Treaſon, in my judgment they might have ſpar'd'em. For why ſhould they be ſo zealous to pray for them, when they would not ſo much as beg one tear from thoſe that were not of their own Profeſſion? They were no Prayers of Charity, but rather the Curſes of their Malice, while they labour'd to ſcandal the Juſtice of ſuch moſt Eminent Judges, the Impartiality of ſo ſound a Jury, and the Fidelity of ſuch Witneſſes, who having ſo highly merited of the whole Nation, have render'd the Sufferers more remarkable in their Ends, than in all the Progreſs of their Lives before.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:93758:5"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
